amnesty.org.au 2016-08-10

# Privacy statement - Amnesty International Australia

**Your privacy is extremely important. Amnesty International Australia is committed to respecting your privacy and upholding the security of your personal information, so you can feel confident when interacting with our vital human rights work.**

This Privacy Statement sets out what personal information we collect and why, and how we collect, hold, use and disclose your personal information.

When you provide personal or sensitive information to us you have an opportunity to register whether you consent to that information being collected, used and disclosed as set out in this Privacy Statement.

Remember, we are here to help with any queries. If you have further questions after reading this Privacy Statement, please get in touch with our Supporter Relations team (details below).

#### What information we collect

**Personal information**

Personal information is information about an identified individual. We collect personal information about individuals including members, supporters, volunteers, contractors, job applicants and people whose human rights we work to protect. The information collected and held generally includes your name, address, date of birth, and contact details (such as your phone numbers, fax number and email address). We also use ‘cookies’ to track visits to our website and encourage you to return to them; you can disable cookies in your internet browsing settings.

You do not have to provide us with your personal information. However if you do not provide us with your personal information, it will be difficult for us to contact you. For example, without your personal information we may not be able to issue you with a receipt, offer you employment, respond to your request for assistance, or provide you with more information about Amnesty’s work.

**Sensitive information**

Sensitive information may include information about ethnic origin, political opinion or philosophical belief. Amnesty may collect and hold sensitive information in order to provide some services. For example, we may collect your ethnic origin if you are a case-work client, and some may view support of international human rights law as a political or philosophical belief. Amnesty will only collect sensitive information directly from you. By providing it to us you consent to us collecting, using or disclosing it as specified by this Privacy Statement or as otherwise authorised by law.

#### How we collect personal information

We collect personal information you provide to us directly, for example, in person, over the phone, by email, through our website or by completing our online or hard-copy petition forms. We may also collect your personal information from publicly available sources, from SMS and other electronic means and from third parties. In the event that we collected your personal information from a third party, we will notify you of that fact.

During your communications with us, please do not provide us with personal or sensitive information of any other individual unless you have the express consent of that individual to do so. If you do provide us with such information about another individual, you:

* must tell that individual that you will be providing their information to us and that we will handle their information in accordance with this Privacy Statement 
* must provide that individual with a copy of (or refer them to) this Privacy Statement 
* warrant that you have that individual's consent to provide their information to us.

#### Use of personal information

We use personal information you provide us for the purpose for which it was provided to us, for other related purposes or as permitted or required by law. Such purposes include:

* processing donations, memberships and Human Rights Defender pledges 
* issuing receipts 
* responding to your comments or questions 
* providing follow-up information about Amnesty’s activities 
* supporter research, for example asking you to participate in a survey about your involvement with Amnesty 
* requesting financial or activism support 
* improving our website 
* measuring the level of support received and the effectiveness of our campaigns 
* providing you with marketing material such as our newsletter (if you opt-in to receive such information) 
* any other purposes identified at the time of collecting your information. 

If we also obtain your sensitive information, we will only use your sensitive information (such as your ethnic origin or health information) for the purposes listed above, or other directly-related purposes or purposes to which you consent.

#### Disclosure of personal information

Any personal information you provide to us may be disclosed, if appropriate, to third parties who provide services on our behalf, such as mail, database, telephone, IT, audit, professional advice, payment processing and research services. We may also disclose your personal information to our volunteers who assist with many of our tasks. From time to time we send personal information to suppliers who are based overseas, such as cloud storage suppliers. The overseas locations of these suppliers include North America, Europe and Asia.

Our suppliers are required by us to comply with the Australian Privacy Principles. We have confidentiality agreements in place with many of our service providers and external agencies, and with staff and volunteers who handle personal information that we provide to them. We will only disclose your personal information for the purposes for which it was initially collected, other directly-related purposes or purposes to which you otherwise consent.

Other than as stated above, we will we not share your personal information. Though unlikely, it is possible that we might be forced to disclose personal information in response to legal process or in good faith when the law requires it, for example, in response to a court order, subpoena or a law enforcement agency's request.

#### Data security

We are committed to protecting your data. We take commercially-reasonable steps to ensure your personal information is protected from misuse, loss, interference and unauthorised access, modification or disclosure. For example, whenever we ask for your financial details online, we use security-encrypted response forms and your information is held in secure servers.

However, data protection and security measures are never completely secure and, despite the measures we have put in place, we cannot guarantee the security of your information. You must take care to protect your personal information (for example, by protecting any usernames and passwords) and you should notify us as soon as possible of any security breaches. If you do not wish to make your financial contribution online, please contact us to receive a hard-copy form.

#### Additional information for website or email use

**Cookies**

When you visit our website, we will collect and store your computer’s assigned IP address, the date and time of your visit, the information accessed and the referring page. We will also collect other non-identifying data for statistical purposes. This information is not linked to your personal information unless required by law.

Like many websites, our website may use ‘cookies’ from time to time. Cookies are small text files that the website transfers to your computer through your web browser to enable the website’s systems to recognise your computer. Cookies may also be used to record non-personal information such as the date, time or duration of your visit, or the pages accessed, for website administration, statistical and maintenance purposes. Any such information will be aggregated and not linked to particular individuals unless required by law. You have the ability to accept or decline cookies by modifying the settings in your browser. Please note that some parts of the website may not function fully for users that disallow cookies.

**Email monitoring**

If you send us an email, the message content may be monitored by our Internet Service Provider or Amnesty employees if email abuse is suspected, or for troubleshooting and maintenance purposes. Email is an unsecure communications medium; it should not be used for confidential correspondence.

**Third party links**

Our website contains hypertext links to other third-party websites. Amnesty is not responsible for the privacy practices or the content of such websites, which are governed by the privacy policy of third parties. Amnesty is not in a position to verify the accuracy of the information or any claims made by third parties.

**List swapping**

Occasionally we allow other like-minded organisations to use your data to contact you with information that might be of interest to you. We will always obtain your express consent for your personal information to be disclosed to a like-minded organisation for this purpose. If we receive your data from another like-minded organisation, we will inform you where we got your information from and obtain your consent to continue to be contacted by Amnesty.

#### Accuracy, access and correction

We take reasonable steps to ensure that the personal information that we collect and hold is accurate, complete and up-to-date. However, we rely on you to advise us of any changes to your personal information to help us maintain accurate, complete and up-to-date information.

We will, on request, provide you with access to the personal information we hold about you unless otherwise required or permitted by law. We will notify you of the basis for any denial of access to your personal information. We will respond to your request within a reasonable period after the request is made.

To request access to your personal information or, if you wish to update or correct your personal information, please contact us via the contact details provided above.

#### Revisions to our privacy statement

We may revise this Privacy Statement or any part of it from time to time. Please review this Privacy Statement periodically for changes. If we make material changes to this Privacy Statement, we will notify you by email or by putting a notice on our home page (www.amnesty.org.au).

Your continued use of our website, or provision of further personal information to us once you have been notified of the revised Privacy Statement constitutes your deemed acceptance of the revised Privacy Statement.

#### Complaints

If you wish to make a complaint about a breach of this Privacy Statement or the privacy principles of the Privacy Act 1988 (Cth), or for a copy of our Privacy Complaints Handling Policy and Procedure, you can contact us using the contact details above. You will need to provide us with sufficient details regarding your complaint as well as any supporting evidence or information.

Our Privacy Officer will investigate the issue and determine how to resolve your complaint. We will contact you if we require any additional information from you and notify you in writing of the outcome of the investigation. If you are not satisfied with our decision, you can contact us to discuss your concerns or complain to the [Australian Information Commissioner](http://www.oaic.gov.au/).

#### Unsubscribing from emails

If you no longer wish to receive emails from Amnesty International Australia, please click the 'unsubscribe' link included in the footer of our emails.

#### Contact us

If you have any questions or concerns about our Privacy Statement please contact us at: Amnesty International Australia, Locked Bag 23, Broadway NSW 2007 or call our Supporter Relations team on 1300 300 920 (9.00 am – 5.00 pm EST) or email [supporter@amnesty.org.au](mailto:supporter@amnesty.org.au?subject=Privacy%20Statement)

_Updated June 2016_

#### Download

**Download[Amnesty International's privacy statement](http://www.amnesty.org.au/resources/activist/AIAPrivacyStatementMay2016.pdf).**
